<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvay to heaven most clearly discovered and the manner how to walk in this way exactly described. With a brief vindication of the Church of England against all her enemies. By Nicholas Philips, late chaplain to his Majesty's garrison in the Isles of Silly.</title>
            <author>Phillips, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213941</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1799:17 or 2074:13b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvay to heaven most clearly discovered and the manner how to walk in this way exactly described. With a brief vindication of the Church of England against all her enemies. By Nicholas Philips, late chaplain to his Majesty's garrison in the Isles of Silly.</title>
                  <author>Phillips, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T. Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The way to heaven.</note>
                  <note>Item at 2074:13b bound with: Loyalty and piety. By Nicholas Philips ... London, : Printed for T. Brown, 1681.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the British Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WAY TO HEAVEN MOST CLEARLY DISCOVERED: AND The manner how to walk in this Way exactly deſcribed.</p>
            <p>With a brief Vindication of the <hi>Church of England</hi>
               <hi>Againſt all her Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Nicholas Philips, <hi>late Chaplain to His Majeſty's Garriſon in the Iſles of</hi> Silly.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 30.21.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the way, walk in it.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Brown,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my Dear Mother,</hi> The Church of England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deareſt Mother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Eſteemed it a great happineſs, that I had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to have my New Birth from thy Womb, and to be ſuckled up from my Cradle with the ſweet Milk of thy ſyncere Doctrine. And if thou be not aſhamed of ſuch a Son, next to my Chriſtianity, I eſteem it my greateſt glory to have had ſuch a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But I eſteem it a greater happineſs, that I had the Grace given me to ſtick to thee in thy adverſity, and not to leave thee, nor to turn from following after thee, when thou wert turn'd from a <hi>Naomy</hi> into a <hi>Marah,</hi> and all thy beauty and pleaſantneſs was chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into deformity and ſorrow.</p>
            <p>But O I eſteem it my greateſt happineſs, that upon the turning of thy Captivity, and the recovering of thy priſtine Beauty and Splendour, thou haſt not cockered me with thy Smiles and Favours (Proſperity being of all eſtates the moſt dangerous Enemy unto Piety) but kept me under with thy Frowns and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, the Furnance of Affliction, always cauſing the Fire of Piety to burn the brighter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:3"/>
            <p>And though the unkindneſs of Friends wound deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than do the Swords of Enemies; yet as no oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foe could, ſo no unkindneſs of Friend ſhall, divorce me from thee. And I am as unſeparably devoted to thee, as <hi>Ruth</hi> was unto her <hi>Naomy; The Lord do ſo to me and more alſo, if ought but Death part thee and me.</hi> And I am immutably,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Dutiful and Obedient, Though Unworthy Son,</hi> Nich. Philips.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Way to Heaven clearly Diſcovered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Acts <hi>2. 47.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are the concluſion of the Hiſtory, which St.
<hi>Luke</hi> gives us, of the firſt gathering of the Holy Catholick Church by the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon his glorious Aſcenſion into Heaven, and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon them at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon the day of <hi>Pentecoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſts Church like a grain of Muſtard Seed, unto which he compares it in the Goſpel, <hi>from a ſmall Seed grew up by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>grees into ſo great a tree,</hi> that it was able in a ſhort time, to afford ſhelter and protection to the <hi>Fouls of the Air,</hi> unto ſuch as from all parts of the world, unto which the Air lies open, ſhould repair unto it: And according to the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Goſpel Prophet <hi>Eſay ch.</hi> 60. <hi>ult. his little one ſoon became a thouſand, and his ſmall one a great Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt at the firſt Gathering of his Church called only the twelve A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. Afterward, he enlarged their number, by adding to them the 70 Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. After his glorious Aſcenſion into Heaven, and when the Church was met together, for the chuſing of an Apoſtle, into the room of the Traitor <hi>Judas,</hi> we find them increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the number of an hundred and twenty, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. But upon the gracious Deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles at Jeruſalem upon the day of Pentecoſt, we find it to grow up ſo faſt that on that very day as is teſtifyed here, <hi>v.</hi> 41. no leſs than 3000 Souls were added unto it.</p>
            <p>And theſe 3000, being by the Apoſtles miraculous ſpeaking of all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, gathered from out of all Nations under Heaven, were
<hi>Primitiae Eccleſiae Catholicea,</hi> The Firſt Fruits of the Holy Catholick Church. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Church had been national, and ſingular, confined within the limits of the Jewiſh Nation, with whom God dealt better than with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, gave his word unto Jacob, his Statutes and Ordinances un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30584:4"/>to Iſrael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19. But from henceforth it grew to be Catholick and Univerſal, extending it ſelf into all Lands, and conſiſting of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all Nations, who though divided in body, are united in Soul, knit together by Faith, as the Members of a Natural Body are by joynts and ſinews in one Communion and Fellowſhip, in the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, having all one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>And that there is no ſalvation to be obtained by any one, of what people, nation or Language, of what Age, Sex, or Condition ſoever, that is not added unto, and made a Member of this Holy Catholick Church: The ſacredly-inſpired penman of the Holy Ghoſt, St. <hi>Luke</hi> here aſſures us, by telling us, That the Lord added to the Church daily, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.</p>
            <p>In handling of which ſacred Maxim and Poſition I ſhall (Grace aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me) ſhew you,
<list>
                  <item>1. What the Church is.</item>
                  <item>2. That Salvation is not to be obtained any other way than by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added unto it.</item>
                  <item>3. That the principal Agent in this work of Salvation is Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and that it is the Lord that daily adds men unto the Church.</item>
                  <item>4. The means and inſtruments, which God ordinarily makes uſe of in this great work of Mans Salvation.</item>
                  <item>5. And laſtly, the means which men, who are put into the ſtate of Salvation, and added to the Church, muſt be careful to uſe, if they will keep themſelves in the Unity and Community of the Church, and in the ſtate of Salvation. And,</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Of the Church.</p>
            <p>Church is a word of various ſignification, and in ſeveral ſenſes ſhall we find it uſed in holy Scripture; but chiefly it ſignifies, and moſtly it is there uſed for the whole number of the Elect, that ever were or ever ſhall be in the world, in what place ſoever, either in Heaven or Earth, they are diſperſed. So that this Holy Catholick Church conſiſts of two principal parts:
<list>
                  <item>1. Of the Triumphant part in Heaven, where the departed Saints, and ſuch as are looſed from the burthen of the fleſh, are rejoycing for the Conqueſt which they have gotten over the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; a ſinging continually of <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> of Songs and Pſalms, and Thankſgivings unto God, for giving them the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the Militant part of Earth, where the living Saints are ſtill a fighting againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; a ſighing for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30584:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>their manifold frailties, and fleſhly corruptions, and a longing to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now though this Militant Church of Chriſt be but one body, and Chriſt ſaith of his Dove, his undefiled one, <hi>That ſhe is but one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the onely one of her Mother, Cant.</hi> 6.9. Yet as the vaſt Ocean, which is but one and the ſame Concourſe of Waters, hath divers Appellations, changeth its Name, and is diſtinguiſhed by the ſeveral Regions on which it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and there is the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ocean, the
<hi>Britiſh</hi> Ocean, the <hi>German</hi> Ocean, and which make but one and the ſame Sea: so the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, which is but one body, hath divers names, and is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the ſeveral Countries wherein the Members of it reſide; and there is the <hi>Greek</hi> Church and the
<hi>Latin</hi> Church, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Church, &amp;c. who though they may differ from each other in ſome Circumſtantial and Extrafundamental Points of Religion, yet ſo long as they agree in the Subſtantial and Fundamental Points there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, have all one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, are all but Members of one and the ſame Holy Catholick Church. One and the ſame Sun ſhoots out from it many Beams of Light, one and the ſame Kingdom hath in it many Counties, one and the ſame Tree many Branches, one and the ſame Body many Members; ſo hath alſo one and the ſame My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Body of Chriſt, <hi>one body but many members,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20.</p>
            <p>Now the true and infallible marks whereby a particular national Church may be known to be a Member of the Holy Catholick One, are (as our Church of <hi>England</hi> hath well ſaid in her Articles of Religion,
<hi>Artic.</hi> 19.) The word of God ſincerely preached, and the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rightly and duly adminiſtred, according to Chriſts Ordinance, and in what ever Congregation of men, profeſſing the Faith of Chriſt, the word of God is ſincerely preached, and the two Eſſential Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Goſpel, Baptiſm, and the Lords Supper, are rightly and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred according to Chriſts Ordinance, by perſons lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſanctified, and ſet apart for the work of the Miniſtry, there is a true branch of the Holy Catholick Church, and with it may any one that profeſſes himſelf a Chriſtian, ſafely joyn, and from it muſt no man that lives within the bounds and limits thereof preſume, to ſeparate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf if he will obtain Salvation.</p>
            <p>And that this Member of the Holy Catholick Church wherein we live, The national Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſuch a Church, we need not make uſe of many words to prove, ſince that which is the beſt of witneſſes, Her works moſt clearly approve and manifeſt it. Her Doctrines ſhe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30584:5"/>confirms n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t by Traditions, Miracles or Dreams, by the Decrees of Councils, or Decretals of Popes, but by the Holy Scriptures, and ſhe ſaith not, <hi>Sic dicit Papa;</hi> but <hi>Sic dicit Dominus.</hi> The bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhe neither ſophiſticates nor mutilates; neither adds to them, nor ſubſtracts from them. In adminiſtring the Sacrament of Baptiſm, ſhe makes no mixture of Salt, Spittle, Oyl, Milk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but makes uſe only of pure Water, and the words of Conſecration which Chriſt himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, <hi>Baptizing with Water, in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> In adminiſtring of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, ſhe doth not make a God of the Bread, and lift it up for the People to Worſhip and Adore; nor doth ſhe think the Wine too good, for any but the Prieſts to drink; but having Bleſſed and Sanctified both Elements with the very words of Conſecration which Chriſt himſelf uſed, ſhe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Inſtitution and Practice, delivers both Bread and Wine into the hand of every particular Communicant.</p>
            <p>Charged is our Church on the one hand by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> with Innovation and Separation; and on the other hand by the <hi>Presbyter</hi> and Sectaries, wi h Popery and Superſtition. And I ſhall crave leave in a word, to vindicate her againſt them both.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who charge us with Innovation and Separation, and ask us where our Church was before <hi>Luther</hi>'s time, we ſay at <hi>Rome,</hi> though lying hid there under a great heap of
<hi>Popiſh</hi> Traſh; and <hi>Luther</hi> with his Aſſociates did but that with better ſucceſs, which others before them had attempted: As the
<hi>Berengarians</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in
<hi>France;</hi> the <hi>Huſſites</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> the
<hi>Wickliiſts</hi> in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> ſhake off the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and Superſtitions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Innovators; but did not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from and forſake the Orthodox, Primitive, Catholick Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> holds no other Doctrine than that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Primitively did, and which St. <hi>Paul</hi> taught them in his Epiſtle unto them, <hi>viz. juſtification only by the bloud of Chriſt.</hi> If upon this Foundation the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have built up a great heap of Wood, and Hay, and Stubble, added as things neceſſary to Salvation, The Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Images, The Invocation of Saints, The Supremacy of the Pope, The lawfulneſs of Depoſing and Murthering of Kings, Maſſes, Merits, Pardons, Purgatory, and a number of the like Traſh, which were never preſcribed by God in his Word, never practiſed in the Church of God, no, not in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, for the firſt Five Hundred Years after Chriſt, they, and not we, are the Innovators, we ſeparated from them no farther than they ſeparated from themſelves, and their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal purity.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30584:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Let the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> return to her ſelf and her original Purity, and though we will not down on our knees and honour her for our Mother, yet we will run with open Arms to embrace her, and will own her for our elder Siſter. And though we will not give her a Supremacy over the reſt of the National Churches of Chriſt, yet we will grant her a primacy in the Church of Chriſt; and becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> was the chief City, and Empreſs of the World, her Biſhop ſhall have the firſt place aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in a General Council, if ever the World be ſo happy as to have one again.</p>
            <p>To the Presbyters and their ſpawn of Sectaries, who charge us with Popery and Superſtition, and ſay that we have borrowed moſt of our Rites and Ceremonies from the Papiſts, we ſay,</p>
            <p>That if nothing which the Papiſts believe and practiſe is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and practiſed by us, we muſt go look for a new God, a new Chriſt, and a new Heaven, as well as a new Religion; for they believe all the Articles of the Three Orthodox Creeds, as well as we, hope to be ſaved by the ſame Chriſt, and to go to the ſame Heaven that we do.</p>
            <p>When the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſeparated from and renounced the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe did not ſeperate from, and renounce what ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the ſacred Scriptures, from the four firſt general Councels and the Orthodox Fathers of the Church, but only from what ſhe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, was brought in and intruded upon the Church of late years by the pride, and avarice, the ſuperſtition and fopperies of the Popes and their Conſiſtories, ſhe piouſly ſeparated the precious from the vile, winnow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away the Chaff from the Wheat, kept what ſhe found pious and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive, but rejected what ſhe found to be ſuperſtitious and novel: Did not caſt away both becauſe the one was nought, and under pretence of reforming utterly deform Religion, did not run from one extream in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, from Idolatry and the worſhipping of Images into profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the not vouchſafing to worſhip God himſelf from a bad reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into no Religion.</p>
            <p>She kept ſuch a Decorum in her carriage, that when ſhe repudiated and caſt off the too too gawdy dreſs of the Babyloniſh Harlot, ſhe leapt not ſtraight with ſome of her Neighbour Siſters into the contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream of a ſlovingly Garb, but having reſpect unto the Apoſtolical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>ult.</hi> ſhe ordered all things in the publick worſhip of God, to be <hi>done decently and in order,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ceremonies uſed in our Church are not many and burdenſom, but few and ſignificant, ſuch as tend to Edification and inſtruction, are not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30584:6"/>
               <hi>Popiſh</hi> and Superſtitious, but Pious and Primitive, have their grounds in the Scripture; the Approbation and Practice of Antiquity, and the Church of Chriſt in all Ages.</p>
            <p>Come, come, <hi>be not more nice than wiſe,</hi> my over preciſe and ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Bretheren; but become ye now at length wiſe unto Salvation. There is a better way ſure to fly from one extream than to run into the other, even to embrace the golden means that lye between: What the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Popiſh,</hi> hath innovated, and is in her Erroneous and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, reject with us and forſake: But what the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it was Chriſtian, and a Depoſitory of the Sacred Truth, hath received from the Sacred Scriptures and Reverend Antiquity, and is in her Pious and Primitive, embrace with us and practiſe. And let us become one, joyn hearts and hands, as well in practiſing the Vertues we find in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as in oppoſing the vices and errours which we find in it.</p>
            <p>Surely they who, for ſuch things as are of an indifferent nature, and which every particular Church hath power to alter and change, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or abrogate, ſeparate from our National Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I have proved to be a true Member of the Holy Catholick Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Salvation to a great hazard; for out of the Church; as ſaith my ſecond poſition, there is no ſalvation to be obtained; the Lord
<hi>adding unto the Church daily ſuch as ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Church is <hi>Via Regia,</hi> the King of Kings High-Way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that there is no way for any one to obtain Salvation, but by being added to it, is moſt plainly demonſtrated unto us by that which St.
<hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.20. calls the Type and Figure of it,
<hi>Noah</hi>'s <hi>Ark:</hi> For as all the People that inhabited the Old World, excepting only thoſe Eight Perſons that entered into the Ark, periſhed in the Flood of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which God brought on the Earth; So all the people of the New World, who enter not into the true Ark, the Church, ſhall be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that dreadful fire, wherewith God will one day burn up both the Heaven and the Earth. And therefore Baptiſm which is the Sacrament of initiation, the door whereby we enter into the Church, is by St. <hi>Peter Ib. v.</hi> 21. ſaid to ſave us, as the Ark did thoſe of the Old World that entered into it.</p>
            <p>Illuſtrated alſo is this Truth unto us in Scripture by divers apt Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and Compariſons.</p>
            <p>Called is the Church, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>A Body,</hi> of which Chriſt is the Head, and every true Believer a Member in particular: Now as the Head doth not impart his influences, and perform the Office of a Head to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30584:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Member that is ſeparated and divided from it: So Chriſt will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Divine Influences of his Saving Grace, and perform the Office of a Saviour unto any one, but only unto ſuch as are united and added to his Body the Church.</p>
            <p>Compared is the Church to a Houſhold, and called <hi>Eph.</hi>
2.19. <hi>The Houſhold of God;</hi> now as the <hi>Pater Familias,</hi> and Maſter of a Houſhold, though he may out of charity ſometimes give unto others, yet makes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion only for thoſe of his own Family; ſo though God out of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe bounty, and gracious goodneſs, imparts his general Mercies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all creatures, preſerveth both Man and Beaſts; cauſeth his Sun to ſhine, and his Rain to fall on good and bad, juſt and unjuſt; yet his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al favours, and ſingular graces he reſerves only for thoſe of his own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Church. He is good to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but chiefly unto thoſe in <hi>Iſrael</hi> who are of a pure heart, ſaith the Prophet,
<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 73.1. He is the Saviour of all men, but eſpecially of thoſe that believe, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.</p>
            <p>Likened is the Church to a City, and called <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.
<hi>The City of the Living God.</hi> Now as a man cannot be protected by the ſtrength of a City, and partake of the priviledges and immunities thereof, unleſs he put himſelf within the Walls, and become a Citizen: So a Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be protected by that ſtrong City which hath Salvation appointed for its Walls and Bulwarks, but only ſuch a one as is admitted into the New
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and become a Fellow Citizen with the Saints.</p>
            <p>Compared is the Church to a Mother, and called <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26.
<hi>The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all True Believers.</hi> Now as no one can live a natural life without a Mother to conceive, bring forth, ſuckle and nouriſh him; ſo no man can live a ſpiritual life, the life of grace here, and of glory hereafter, who is not begotten of the immortal ſeed of the Word, of his Mother the Church, regenerated and new-born, who is not fed and nouriſhed up in ſound Doctrine by the ſincere Milk which iſſueth forth of her two Breaſts, the Books of the Old and New Teſtament: And in this ſence it is a trite and common ſaying among the Ancient Fathers, <hi>That he ſhall not have God for his Father, who hath not the Church for his Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likened is the Church by our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 15.1. to a Vine, of which as he there tells us he is the heart, his Elect the Branches, now as that Branch cannot bear fruit except it abide in the Vine, <hi>no more can ye,</hi> ſaith he to his Diſciples there, <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>except ye abide in me,</hi> intimating thereby moſt plainly, that unleſs we be ingraſted into Chriſt the true Vine, and added to his Church, we can have no true hopes of obtaining Life and Salvation through him. Since it is confirmed then unto us by ſuch a cloud
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30584:7"/>of Witneſſes, that out of the Church there is no Salvation to be obtained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Groſs and abſur'd is the opinion of thoſe Libertines who think a man may be ſaved in any Religion; So he live an outward moral civil Life. The Jew in his Judiaſm. The Turk in his Mahometiſm. The Heathen in his Paganiſm. They may as well ſay that a man might be ſaved in the Flood out of the Ark, by climbing up to the top of ſome Houſe, or Tree, or Mountain. That a man being ſeparated from the body may live, a branch Cut off from a Tree bear fruit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Fearful and dangerous is the eſtate of thoſe Athieſts and ſenſual worldlings, who neither regard any Church, nor think on any religion at all, but live like beaſts always grazing in the earth and never ſo much as lift up their hearts or eyes to heaven.</p>
            <p>Ravenous Ravens may, I grant, find pleaſure and preſent relief, out of the Ark. And profane Eſauites, may think themſelves happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in having plenty of belly chear and temporal bleſſings. But the innocent ſpotleſs Dove when out of the Ark can find no place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where to ſet the ſole of her feet on till ſhe return thither again. And a true Iſraelite when he hath with King <hi>Solomon</hi> tryed all the things in the world, pleaſures, riches, honour, will in the end conclude with him, that all worldly things are vanity and vexation of Spirit. And that there is no true content, nothing that can ſatisfie a mans mind, no hope of Salvation to be had any where, but in the true Ark of Gods Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Damnable is the eſtate, and on the very brink of hells pit are the feet of thoſe Factious and Schiſmatical Spirits, who out of pride and ſingularity of heart, or becauſe they diſguſt ſome of the outward ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ceremonies of our Church, forſake the Society of the faithful, ſeparate themſelves from the lawful allowed Church aſſembly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to Conventicles and private meetings, where having no lawful al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed prieſts to officiate, they cannot have the word of God ſincerely Preached, nor the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred according to Chriſts Ordinance; for though it be granted lawful for private perſons within the limits of their own family to open and expound the Scripture ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their talent; yet he who without a lawful call and miſſion ſhall preſume in a publick Congregation to handle and expound the word. Though he handle it never ſo well and expound it never ſo truely, yet doth he not preach nor is his Doctrine ſufficiently qualified for the Salvation of Souls. For how can they Preach except they be ſent, demands the Apoſtle,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. proving moſt plainly by this his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogative
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30584:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that effectual Preaching, ſuch as is ſufficiently qualified for the Salvation of Souls, is the proper work of the Miniſtry, of thoſe that are lawfully Called and Sent forth to execute this publique function in the Church. And no man, as ſaith the Apoſtle,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. may take this hence to himſelf, but he that is called of God as was <hi>Aaron (i.e.)</hi> unleſs he have as <hi>Aaron</hi> had, not only an inward call and inclination of the Spirit, but alſo an outward one, and a ſolemn ordination to the ſacred function.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Since there is no Salvation to be had out of the Church, and the Lord addeth daily unto the Church ſuch as ſhall be ſaved! Oh how infinitely are they bound to be thankful unto God, and alwayes to praiſe and bleſs his holy name, who find themſelves to be placed in the ſtate of Salvation, or made viſible Members of the holy Catholick Church; for it is not by their own natural inclination, nor by the care or piety either of their natural or ſpiritual Fathers, (though theſe be good helps and means) that men are placed in the ſtate of Salvation and added to the Church, but by the exceeding goodneſs, mercy and grace of God. And it is as ſaith my third poſition, the Lord that daily adds unto the Church ſuch as ſhall be ſaved. God is the principal agent in the great work of mens Salvation, he is the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, the beginner and perfecter of every good work, yea he that worketh in us both to will and to do of his good pleaſure, as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rebecca</hi> may look the Veniſon, but it is
<hi>Iſaac</hi> that muſt give the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; <hi>Paul</hi> may plant and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but it is God that gives the increaſe. He he it is, who perſwades wild <hi>Japhet</hi> to come and dwell in the tents of gentle <hi>Sem,</hi> that being men, as the Apoſtle phraſeth it, that were born Aliens from the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Strangers and Forreigners, to become fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God.</p>
            <p>Now this work of mans regeneration, of his being begotten a new in the Goſpel, and added to the Church, God works not extroardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, by miracle, but ordinarily by means. And the ordinary means which God makes uſe of for the perfecting of this great work, we may find here in this Chapter, by the means which he uſed for the making of this great addition to the Church of 3000 Souls, to be the word preached, faith to apprehend and belive it, and baptiſm to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and Seal it.</p>
            <p>Theſe primitive Converts had the word preached unto them by Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> And being convicted in their Conſciences of the Truth of it,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30584:8"/>they believ'd it. And applying themſelves to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles for advice what to do that they might be ſaved, they were preſcribed by them the baptiſm of repentance for the remiſſion of their ſins. Repent, and be baptiſed every one of you in the name of the Lord Jeſus for the remiſſion of ſins, <hi>v.</hi> 38. And they as it is teſtified, <hi>v.</hi> 41. thankfully embraced his advice, gladly received his word, were immediately baptized, and on that very day there was an addition made unto the Church of no leſs than 3000 Souls.</p>
            <p>And of theſe initiating grounding Ordinances and Graces I would more largely diſcourſe, but that I remember you are perſons, who being born of Chriſtian Parents, and within the pale of the Church, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by Baptiſm added to the Church, and made viſible Members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and therefore it is more ſeaſonable and neceſſary to ſhew you the way and means which you muſt be careful to uſe, if you will keep your ſelves in the Church and the State of Salvation; and this if you will do, you muſt take theſe Primitive Chriſtians here at the 42. <hi>v.</hi> for your pattern; For they being by Baptiſm added to the Church, continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and breaking of Bread, and in Prayer.</p>
            <p>And of theſe Four precious, preſervative, confirming Chriſtian Duties I ſhall now by Gods gracious aſſiſtance orderly diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the Apoſtles Doctrine: By the Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles is here ſignified that form of ſound Doctrine, concerning Chriſt and his being the true Meſſiah promiſed unto the Fathers, which the bleſſed Apoſtles firſt <hi>viva voce</hi> in their Sermons and Harangues deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto the people, and afterwards for the inſtruction of the Church unto the worlds end, wrote in their Goſpels and Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>This contains in it all things neceſſary unto Salvation, both as to the <hi>credenda,</hi> and what we are to believe; and to the
<hi>agenda,</hi> and what we are to do. And he who being by Baptiſm received into, and added to the Militant Church on earth, receives nothing as an Article of Faith, and receſſary to be believed, but what can immediately be induced out of the holy Scriptures; and who in matters of Obedience reſigns up himſelf wholly to the practice of thoſe Rules and Directions, which are given us in the wholeſom words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs, ſhall not fail in due time to be made a glorious Member of the Church Triumphant in Heaven. And able are holy Scriptures to make a man wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus, as it is written, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30584:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Surely he who to Heaven will be directed aright, muſt neither be guided by the falſe fire of the Conclave or the Conventicle, muſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rely on unwritten Traditions, nor on unwarranted Revelations; but muſt make that bright ſhining and unerring light, Gods holy Word, his onely Director and Guide, muſt neither add to it, nor diminiſh from it; muſt neither turn to the right hand and do more, nor to the left hand and do leſs, than is enjoyned him in the holy Scriptures. And accurſed be he, yea though he be an Angel from Heaven, that ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to preach any other Doctrine, contrary to that which the holy Apoſtles have delivered unto us, ſaith S.
<hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>A Treaſury full of all manner of precious Stones is Gods holy Word, and there is no one of what condition or quality, ſex or age ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, but hath his particular Rule given him in the Scripture, and may if he come to the hearing or reading of Gods holy Word, with an heart humbled and willing to be inſtructed, find what he in his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vocation and calling muſt eſpecially do and perform, what he muſt eſpecially ſhun and avoid.</p>
            <p>And 'tis indeed the Reformation of thoſe Abuſes which we commit in our particular Callings, wherein the power of Grace and Religion doth moſt eſpecially appear. Religion, Religion, my Brethren, is not a thing merely of publick and common profeſſion; it dwells not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Churches and Temples; no, it hath a principal reſpect to the well ordering of our particular and perſonal Callings; it ſaith to us as Chriſt did to the man in the Goſpel, whom he diſpoſſeſſed of a Legion of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, Go home to thy Houſe, and let thy behaviour and carriage there, evidence and ſhew forth the truth and ſincerity of thy Religion.</p>
            <p>We read <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.20. that the <hi>Jews</hi> were commanded to write Gods Law not onely on the Doors of their Temples, but alſo on the Doors of their Houſes, that ſo they might meditate and think on it to do it, not onely on the Sabbath and holy Solemnities, when they were called upon to go up into the Houſe of the Lord; but all the days of their life, and as oft as they went in and out at their own Doors; that ſo they might learn to regulate their perſonal Imployments, and the works of their particular Callings, according to thoſe Directions which are given by God in his holy Law. And 'tis indeed according to the ordering of our ſelves in our particular Callings, that God will proceed with us at the laſt day; and when ſummoned to appear before his dreadful Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, we ſhall not be called to give an account of other mens Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, but of our own, and how we have demeaned our ſelves in that ſtate of life, wherein he hath been pleaſed to place us.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:30584:9"/>
            <p>Surely Brethren, if we who have the Goſpel printed amongſt us, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at home in our Houſes, and I hope read therein every day: If we who have the Goſpel preached amongſt us, and may if we be not ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and negligent on every Lords day, hear it expounded and applied in our Churches and Synagogues, would inſtead of curiouſly inquiring out of it with S.
<hi>Peter,</hi> what is other mens duty and required of them; ſet our ſelves with S. <hi>Paul</hi> to inquire out of it what is our duty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us in that ſtation wherein God hath placed us; and ſet our ſelves ſincerely about the doing of it, we ſhould moſt clearly manifeſt our ſelves to be true Members of his Militant Church on earth, and ſhould not fail in due time to be made glorious Members of his Church Triumphant in Heaven.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which you muſt learn of thoſe primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, if after you have been added to the Church, you will continue and preſerve your ſelves in the Church, is to continue ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Fellowſhip. By Fellowſhip with the Apoſtles is here ſignified conformity unto them, in thoſe laudable and decent Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Cuſtoms, and Orders, that were practiſed by them in their Church Aſſemblies and publick Meetings. In which whoſoever refuſeth to have Community and Fellowſhip with that Church, into which he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by Baptiſm, and of which he is made a Member, is void not onely of all Religion, but even of all Reaſon and common Civility.</p>
            <p>The actions of Religion and Divine Worſhip are twofold, either Eſſential and ordinate, or circumſtantial and ſubordinate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The eſſential and ordinate parts of divine Worſhip are Faith and Holineſs of Life, and our Rule for this muſt be Gods Holy Word, and we muſt receive nothing as an Article of Faith, a thing abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto ſalvation, which cannot be immediately deduced out of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The circumſtantial and ſubordinate Actions of Religion, are the time, the place, the veſture, the geſture, which are required to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our performance of Church Duties; and theſe things being not abſolutely determined of God in his Holy Word, are left to the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Church: And God in that general warrant which he has given the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>ult. Let all things be done decently and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> hath impowred her to cut out and ſhape each particular decency and order, as will beſt ſuit with the condition, the comlineſs, and the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every particular National Church: and it is no more neceſſary that all Churches ſhould obſerve one and the ſame Rites and Ceremonies, than it is that all Nations ſhould wear one and the ſame kind of cloaths.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30584:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Surely theſe Orders and Ordinances, Rites and Ceremonies, which by our lawful Superiors, we are enjoyned to obſerve in our. Church meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Aſſemblies, though they cannot immediately be deduced out of Gods Holy Word; yet if they be not contrary unto it, but ſerve for decency and comlineſs in the ſervice of God, are part of thoſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, unto which we are commanded by St <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. to ſubmit for the <hi>Lords ſake:</hi> And therefore though pride or arrogancy, contempt or neglect, to violate and break the eſtabliſhed Order of the <hi>Church,</hi> is to be guilty of no leſs crime than Diſobedience to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of God; Indeed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which our Tranſlators here ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> is the very word, which St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.3. uſeth to fignify the
<hi>Collections</hi> and <hi>Comributions,</hi> which were made for the poor, and that in this ſenſe it is to be taken here, is the opinion of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, judicious Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> in his Annotations on that place.</p>
            <p>Piouſly, indeed with great praiſe to themſelves, and much comfort to the afflicted, Members of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were
<hi>Collections</hi> for the poor ordained by the Apoſtles to be uſed in their Church meetings, <hi>As I have given or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Church of</hi> Galatia, <hi>Even ſo do yee</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) to his
<hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1 on the firſt day of the week,
<hi>Let every one lay by of his ſtore as God hath proſpered him for the poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though the practice of this Apoſtolical, Primitive, and moſt Chriſtian duty be ſtrictly injoyned in our Liturgy, to be uſed on every Lords day, and ſolemn Feſtival, and after the Sermon is ended, the Prieſt is required to return to the Lords Table; and thereby reading ſome Select portions of Scripture, to ſtir up the people to acts of Alms-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Charity and Piety; yet to the eternal ſtain of the Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Prieſts and people be it ſpoken, it is but in very few places obſerved.</p>
            <p>Many of our Prieſts who ſeem to be zealous obſervers of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of our Church, are notwithſtanding to ſave their own purſes, and becauſe they will not give good example unto others, very looſe in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing this principal part of it, and rarely or never (unleſs upon ſome extraordinary occaſion) do they ſtir up their people to Almſgiving, and Charity, expoſing themſelves thereby to that woe which our ſaviour in the Goſpel pronounced againſt the Scribes and Phariſees,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. for their ſtrict obſerving the leſſer matters of the law, the tything of Mint, Anniſe, and Cummin, and their neglect of the weightier mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof, the practiſe of Judgment, Mercy and Faith.</p>
            <p>And though moſt of our people think that their ready and chearful paying of theſe rates, and taxes, which are required of them, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30584:10"/>of the poor and the repairing of the Church, will excuſe them for not giving any thing at the Offertory; yet they muſt know that in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe rates and taxes there is nothing of Religion, more then obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto the Law, and it is no more than Turks and Pagans, if they lived amongſt us, ſhould pay, or than the Heriticks and Schiſmaticks that do live amongſt us, do pay. God approves of no forced oblations and nought but Free-Will offerings will pleaſe him: and therefore if you will find favour in his ſight, and be accepted when you preſent your ſelves before him, you muſt not come empty handed, but muſt bring your preſents with you when you come into his Courts, ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 96.8. your gifts when you come to his Altar, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.13.</p>
            <p>Never, Oh never think brethren, that God who hath given you all that you have, will accept at your hands thoſe cheap ſacrifices of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Praiſe, or Hearing, that loſt you but a little lip and ear-labour. You know who it was that ſaid, It is a more bleſſed thing to give, then to receive. And there is aſſuredly more of Chriſtianity and true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in one merciful tender hearted, compaſſionate act of mercy and charity, than there is in the fruitleſs hearing of an hundred Sermons, or in the vocal uttering a thouſand Prayers and Praiſes.</p>
            <p>And verily, if men would but ſpare ſomething out of their weekly ſuperfluities and idle expences, to bring with them on Gods day, to Gods houſe, there to offer it up unto him as a Teſtification of their gratitude, and thankfulneſs unto him for the many Mercies he hath beſtowed upon them, they would find it ſo far from impairing, that it would improve their eſtates, and draw down a bleſſing upon all the works of their hands: The</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thing that we muſt learn of theſe Primitive Chriſtians, if we will keep and preſerve our ſelves in the Church and in the State of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, is to be conſtant Gueſts at Gods holy Table, and to continue ſtedfaſt in the breaking of bread, <hi>for they, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By breaking of bread is here ſignified the holy Communion and the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, in the Celebration of which, for our better apprehenſion of his Death and Paſſion, and to ſet him forth as it were evidently crucified before our Eyes, our Lord commanded that bread ſhould be broken, and Wine poured out, and delivered to the Church and Congregation of the Faithful.</p>
            <p>Breaking of bread and eating of bread are oft, I grant in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament uſed to ſignifie, an ordinary and common meal; but in the New Teſtament, eſpecially after our Saviours inſtituting of his holy Supper,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30584:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is uſed to ſignifie the Holy Communion of the Body and Bloud of our Lord; and in this ſenſe it is not only uſed here, but alſo in <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. And in this ſenſe it is ſtill uſed by ſome of our Sectaries, who u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually expreſs the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, by the terms of breaking of bread.</p>
            <p>And verily the thankful remembrance of his Death, which Chriſt hath required of us, <hi>ſo oft as we eat of this Brend, and drink of this Cup,</hi> ſhould to manifeſt the gratitude that lodges in our heart and that we always carry about in our Bodies, <hi>the dying of the Lord Jeſus</hi> be always <hi>(i.e.)</hi> as oft as opportunity is offered, celebrated in us.</p>
            <p>Seldom met the Fathers of our Faith, the Apoſtles, and primitive Chriſtians (eſpecially on the Lords Day) but they had with the Word preached and Prayer, the Holy Sacrament alſo adminiſtred among them: And in imitation of this Apoſtolical primitive practiſe, it is the conſtitution of our Mother the <hi>Church of England,</hi> That the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper, ſhould in Cathedral and Collegiate <hi>Churches</hi> (where there are many Prieſts and Deacons, who being Chriſts menial Servants ought chiefly to commemorate his Death) ſhould on every Lords Day and Feſtival be adminiſtred, in Oppidal and great Congregations monthly, in Rural and the leaſt Aſſemblies quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly: And to mind the people of this moſt Chriſtian Duty, and to ſhew his readineſs to adminiſter, if the people were piouſly diſpoſed to receive the Holy Sacrament, is the Prieſt by the Rubrick of our Church injoyned on every <hi>Lords Day</hi> and
<hi>Feſtival</hi> to ſtand at the Communion Table, and there to read all the Communion Service appointed for that Day.</p>
            <p>No greater teſtimony aſſuredly can any man give of his Chriſtianity, and that he is truly thankful unto God for giving his Son to dye for his ſins, and hopeful by virtue of his death to eſcape eternal death and damnation, than when he finds joy and delight and ſpiritual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in that great miſtery of our Religion, the oft communicating and feeding on the Body and Bloud of his Saviour, the only means which he hath ordained, to make us always mindful of what he did and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us. This this, the truely Pious man wiſhes, might not only be his yearly, quarterly, and monthly food; but even his daily bread, and he is even ſick of ſpiritual hunger when he comes to the Church and finds not a Communion there.</p>
            <p>And ſurely they who when the Holy Sacrament is adminiſtred in that particular Church and Congregation, whereof they are members, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe (without ſome lawful cauſe, and impediment) to come and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30584:11"/>with the Church, <hi>ipſo facto Excommunicate,</hi> and put themſelves, out of the ſtate of Salvation. The,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thing which we muſt learn of theſe primitive Chriſtians here, is to continue ſtedfaſt in prayer. <hi>For they, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Prayer, is not here meant private prayer, the prayers that are compoſed by private perſons, and ſaid in private places; but by prayer is here meant publick or common Prayer, the Apoſtles Prayer, the Churches Prayer; ſuch Prayers as by the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors the Governors of the Church are compoſed for the uſe of the Church, with which all the Congregation are well acquainted, in which they may all ſafely joyn, and unto which they may all chearfully ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer is indeed a Duty unto the performance of which God hath oft in Scripture made promiſe of Salvation, but no Prayers are ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto him, or ſo pleaſant with him, as are publick and common prayers: And never are his ears ſo open to hear, nor his mercy ſo ready to grant requeſts, as when he is called upon in the voice of his Church, and all the Congregation of the faithful joyn together in prayer with one Accord, as did the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.14. when with one voice, and one heart, with one mouth, and with one mind, with the ſame words, and the ſame Spirit they preſented their Supplications unto him.</p>
            <p>And though ſome of our Prieſts, who are more obſervant of the Peoples humour, than of the Conſtitutions of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſeek ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain applauſe to themſelves, than glory to their God, uſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Geneva Mode,</hi> a private ſpirited Prayer of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, in the publick <hi>Congregation,</hi> before their Sermon; yet in ſo doing they not only croſs the practice of the primitive
<hi>Church,</hi> which never allowed any thing to be ſaid before the Sermon, but the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> or <hi>gemina Salutatio,</hi> but alſo the Orders and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of our National <hi>Church,</hi> which inſtead of allowing any ſuch thing, expreſly forbids it in her 55
<hi>Canon:</hi> no private ſpirited prayer then being allowed to be uſed in our <hi>Church,</hi> no ſuch Prayer can be uſed, without wilful and manifeſt contempt and diſobedience, which as we are aſſured, 1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. will mar the beſt of Sacrifices and make them unacceptable unto God.</p>
            <p>And as no Prayers ought to be ſaid in the publick
<hi>Congregation,</hi> but the Apoſtles Prayer, the Churches Prayer, Common-Prayer; ſo in the performance of this Duty, we muſt be ſtedfaſt and permanent, and with theſe primitive Chriſtians, continue ſtedfaſtly in prayer: And ſurely ſuch an Apoſtolical, ſuch a primitive, ſuch a religious way of ſerving God doth our Church preſcribe in her
<hi>Liturgy,</hi> that ſhe endeavours to make our whole <hi>Life</hi> Angelical and Divine; for it not only preſcribes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30584:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Form of Prayer to be uſed; on Sundays and Holydays, but a Form to be uſed on every day of the week. And the Curate that miniſtreth in every particular <hi>Church</hi> or
<hi>Chappel</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> is bound by the <hi>Rubris</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> daily Morning and Evening to ſay <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> wherein he <hi>Miniſtreth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be the Lords Remembrancer daily morning and evening, to mind him of the peoples wants, and to intercede for them, is, what ever the world thinks of it, the chief and principal part of the Prieſtly office: But alas ſuch Prieſts are here now a days as rare to be found, as black ſwans: And the world had not more cauſe of old, to complain of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching Miniſters, than ſhe has now of unminiſtring Preachers, moſt Miniſters contenting themſelves with a ſingle preachment on the Lords day, altogether neglecting the principal parts of their Prieſts office, daily morning and evening to offer up unto God the Prayers and Praiſes of the Church in behalf of the people.</p>
            <p>I know the Prieſts are wont to lay the fault on the People, and to ſay that they will not come to joyn with them in Prayer, on the week days; and the People again retort it back upon the Prieſts, and ſay that they will not be conſtant and continue in the practiſe of this duty: But to ſpeak truth to the ſhame of both parties, it is from the profaneſs and impiety, the worldlineſs and wickedneſs that now a days harbours in the hearts, both of Paſtor and People, that this Heavenly imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is altogether neglected amongſt us, and men can find time for the doing of any thing, rather than the ſervice of God. But let him go (what ever he be) both for a worldly and a wicked one too, who thinks he can make better uſe of his time, than to beſtow it upon God, and his ſervice, or that any part of his time is better ſpent, than that which is ſpent in his houſe in Prayer and Praiſes.</p>
            <p>A man may I grant build a Church in his boſom, and ſerve God in his heart, though he never cloath his thoughts with words, and he doth ſo whenever with holy <hi>Hannah</hi> he prayeth ſilently in his heart unto God. A man may build a Church at his beds ſide, and he doth ſo, whenever he doth humbly proſtrate himſelf in prayer before God. A man may make a Church of his Houſe, and he doth ſo as oft as he there with his Family offers up the Sacrifice of Prayer and Praiſe unto God. But oh! it is the higheſt exaltation, the nobleſt Devotion of a truly pious Soul, when it praiſeth God in his Sanctuary, praiſeth him in the Congregation of his Saints; and he is with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 122.1. <hi>Even raviſhed with joy and gladneſs,</hi> whenever he is called upon to go into the Houſe of the Lord to perform this.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30584:12"/>
            <p>Pray, pray, pray, my beloved Brethren, always, in all places, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, but by no means neglect ye the publick Prayers of the Church. Carry always about within you good thoughts and pious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, and live ye holily and well, ſo ſhall you make a Temple of your bodies, and have always a Church within you. Govern well your own families, and bring up your Children and Servants, in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, and let the Burnt offering of prayer, and praiſe be daily Morning and Evening, offered up there; ſo ſhall you always dwell in Hallowed ground, and have with <hi>Philemon,</hi> a Church at home in your own houſe. But O let your feet never fail to to tread Gods Courts, and to frequent his houſe of prayer, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver publick common Prayer (though nothing elſe) be ſaid there, ſo ſhall you manifeſt your ſelves, to be Gods menial and houſhold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and ſhall not fail to partake of the bleſſings which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.5, to thoſe that dwell in his houſe and are always praiſing him,
<q>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30584:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
